Hi, and welcome back to the channel of Perl Tutorial
This time I'm going to talk about
a number of subroutines
functions, that can handle strings in perl
There are couple of basic ones like...
Let's switch to the other window
So, there are couple of basic functions, for example
lc, that will return a lowercase version of a string
uc, that will return uppercase version
and length that will return a number of characters in that string
So, I wrote a couple example files
What you can see here is $str, which is a string
HeLlo with a capital L here and lowercase l
And if you run the script
Lets run it, so you can see, how it acually works
You see, that the first will return "hello" in lowercase
The second one in all uppercase
and the last one just returns the number of characters
Neither of these acually change the string
if you want to change the string, than you type in:
$str = lc $str;
and than you print out the $str again
If I run this now than you will see that
now $str is already lowercase
These are really the simple ones
There is one slightly more complex function
which is called index
Index will get normally two parameters
one of them is string like this one
Let's enlarge the font
the first parameter is a string
and that's what you can see here
and the second one is also a string
that is usually shorter
because you're looking for it's location within the first parameter
so, if you run index on this longer string, giving it "cat"
it will return you 10
because "cat" starts from the 10. character
index called for the starting character is 0
so this capital T is actually 0
that's how it comes to 10 at "c"
If I run this same index function, now giving it "dog"
than it will return -1
because in this string there is only a cat
there is no "dog"
The way it returns error or faliture is giving us -1
If you call this function giving a string
that doesn't appear in the original string you'll get -1
It might be not the most convenient way
but that's what we have to use
If I run index on the string "The", capital T
it will return 0
That's just showing, that the index is 0 based
So it will find this "The" at the beginning
and it will return 0, because that's how it starts
Next call, this one, returns 26
because index is looking for the exact, same string
and it's case sensitive as well
so first "The" doesn't fit, because that's a capital T
so it will look for another "the" and there it will find it
Now, you might think index is looking for the word
but it's not the case, it just looks
for a substring, which is just characters one after another
In the next example you can see
that we are looking for the string
letter "e" and the space afterwards
and it will return us 2
because here you can see
highlighted the place where it appears
but as you can see there is a "e " here
the way you can reach that is index can get third parameter
that's here the number 3, but can be any number
and it will start searching from the third position
which is acually 4th character
beacuse you start counting form 0
so the third place, place number three
and therefore it will find the "the" here
at this spot, which is appearentely the 28. place
Similarly, if I call index and give it character "e"
just for looking
but I give it the number 3 to start from
than it will find the letter "e"
lets see...
so this in the word "jumped"
there is character "e"
so that's what its going to be found
Obviously this 3 can be any number here
so if I can start from 5
and it will return the same value
Lets run this script
So, you can see that the values are:
10, -1, 0, 26, 2, 28, 18
this is the same value
It doesn't matter where you start exactly
as long as you start before
the appearence of the substring
And that's what index does
but there is also function called rindex
that does the same just looking
from the right hand side
It's interesting
if there're multiple apperances of the same string
and it will find the rightmost one of it
Running rindex on the same string
and giving it the substring "e"
than it will return 39
because it will find this letter "e"
And rindex can also have a third parameter
that will tell it where to start from
The position to start from looking for
So if I give it 38
than it will find this letter "e" here
returning 38
And if I start from 37 here
than it will, probably, find this "e" returning 33
So that's about index
The last one, which is probably the most interesting one
out of the functions that I'm showing now
is substring
Substring is actually the opposite of index
In index you would know what you're looking for
what string you're looking for
just don't know where it is
So you're looking for a location
In substring you know the location
you just don't know what is there
and you want to see what is in that location
Substring will get normally a string,
again this "The black cat climbed the green tree";
a number, which is an offset, so it is the location
to beginning of the substring we are looking for
in this original string,
again it's 0 based, so 0 would mean the first character
and 4 means this "b";
and the third parameter is the length
of the substring we are fetching
So because it has 5 characters
it will return the string, starting from this letter "b"
...5 characters, so that's the word "black"
Substring returns those values
and obviously I can assign it to...
what acually I showed you in lc and index example
... you can assign that value to some kind of variable
Here too, I'm just lazy so I'm just printing it out immediately
This call will return the word "black"
Now in the next example you can see
that the length is a negative number
So how would a negative number come there?
Instead of using that as a real length
what Perl does, is saying that this "4" means
how many characters from the left to leave off
and this number now says
how many characters from the right not to include
So, basically, it says count 4 from the left,
count 11 from the right
and whatever is in the middle
- that's what I want to get back
So that's how the "black cat climbed the" is returned
You can even leave off the whole third parameter at all
and that would mean in this case, as you can see:
just give me string from the position 14 to the end
because I didn't see how long it should take
So you just give it: from the position to the end
And here you can see,
that even the first parameter, the location
can be a negative number
and that, as you propably already guessed,
is counting from the end
So instead of saying it's a the length less 4
you just say less 4
and that means: start from this position
And because in this example here
I didn't give the number of characters
so, it will give me all the string till the end
that's just the 4 letters "tree"
Obviously, as you can see in this example,
you can give the third parameter as well
and than it will return you
the two characters from the last four
and that's "tr"
Let's just run it, so we can see
that's the "tr" here, right
And, if I change it a little bit,
for example put "1" here,
than run it and you can get only the "t"
And, if I would give "3" and run,
than I get "tre", so that you can understand it
The last example is a bit funky
So up untill now this call returned substring,
but the original $str, the original string didn't change
In the last example, the return value is still the same
it's defined by the first three parameters
but in the last example, this example
we also have fourth parameter,
which is, in this case, a string containing "jumped from"
And what happends is that, in this case,
Perl substring function will replace the string
that was defined by this three parameters
will replace that substring by the new string
So, because 14, 7 here defines the word "climbed" here,
the return value, in $z, will be "climbed",
but the $str will have a different content
and the word "climbed" will be replaced by the word "jumped from",
by the two words, substring actually
In this case $str will contain:
"The black cat jumped from the green tree"
And as you can see, Perl doesn't care that
the new string, new substring is actually longer
than the original one
it will just make enough space in the string
or if you leave it out, so for example
Let's just run it again
so you can see that
"The black cat jumped from the green tree"
that works
What happens, if I just put in the letter "j"
and run it? Than you will see that
"The black cat j the green tree"
whatever that would mean
It doesn't really matter, what the lengths are relative to each other
You can input an empty string,
but you have to have it here
and than Perl substring will cut out that part of the string
and leave, in this case, two spaces,
because the space before word "climbed"
and the space after
So, that's about substring
I hope you've learned something
and we will return to the next part
and if you are watching it on YouTube
please subscribe to the channel
Thank you, bye bye